This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guests are Adrian Kennard and Kevin
Horton. Adrian has worked in software
and telecommunications for over 40
years. Watched the internet from the
start. He's worked for STL, Nokia,
worked on GSM standards, and even on
toll machines for race tracks. He's an
IPv6 and open software advocate with
lots of published work on GitHub. He
currently works at Andrews and Arnold
AAISP, which he started over 25 years
ago and is the founder and lead
developer of Firebrick routers and
firewalls.
Kevin has worked in hardware and
software and telecommunications since
the early 1980s. He's enjoyed
microcontrollers that range from 4 to 64
bits, power electronics. He's a
experience in communication and network
technologies from serial,
PSTN, and ISDN through 10 gigabit
Ethernet. He currently works at
WatchFront Limited. He started in 1989
and is a founder and lead hardware
designer of Firebrick routers and
firewalls. Adrian and Kevin, welcome to
Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you.
Is there anything I missed in your bio
that you'd like to add or did we cover
everything?
I think that's fairly comprehensive.
that's fine, yeah. I never know what to
say about myself.
Just a a note for you guys and and the
listeners, this is my first ever show
where I've had two guests, so hopefully
it won't be messy. Just need to bear in
mind that we're going to chat over each
other potentially. I'm really looking
forward to this, but you'll need to eat
to take your turn, however excited you
get. That's the risk.
So, we're going to have a chat about
five or six topics, hopefully about 10
minutes each, related to the creation of
the Firebrick router, which you can tell
me more about in a minute. So, let's
start. Adrian and I, correct in my
understanding that you designed and
built an ISP carrier grade router from
scratch.
Well, it it takes a little bit of
explaining here because this is a a
series of products over more than two
decades. So, what we started with was
was a much smaller product. But yes, we
do now have equipment that is in ISP
networks such as ours and Kevin's and
many others that handles many thousands
of customers broadband connections as a
full ISP grade router. So, yes.
So, why on earth did you decide to build
your own hardware and software from
scratch?
Uh-huh.
Shall I let Kevin explain a bit about
the hardware to start with then?
Yeah, thanks. That'd be great.
Well, back in 1999 when we started this,
there wasn't anything like what there is
now just available off the shelf.
My background's in designing industrial
control equipment and things and we
figured, well, how hard is it to do such
a thing? We basically need a
microcontroller with enough resources,
some ethernet controllers. How difficult
could it be to do that? And we were
literally sat around talking about such
things one day and we decided, let's do
this. Adrian's side was software, mine
hardware. From a hardware point of view,
it was very much a mainstream thing that
we did at the time, designing with
microcontrollers and got the data sheets
and started putting a design together.
Meanwhile, talking to Adrian about what
software are we going to run on this
thing?
It does seem like a common thread we
hear the sentence, how difficult can it
be? You know, you have no idea what you
getting into, but you give it a shot
anyway.
Yeah, I think that perhaps should be our
motto, how hard can it be? Yes.
And and now we know how hard it is.
So, could you give me an overview of the
main components, probably version one or
something that you created to give
listeners an idea of
Absolutely.
shouldn't have taken on.
Well, by modern standards, it's very,
very primitive. It was a a good for its
time Hitachi microcontroller, the H8S
family, which is basically a 16-bit
machine. We had two Ethernet controllers
running at the speed of 10 megabits a
second on it, an Ethernet hub, and about
a megabyte of RAM, and some flash memory
built into the thing. If anybody's
interested in the specifics, an H8S/F
2357F
microcontroller.
I'll get some links off you and put it
all in the show notes for
By all means, yeah. And it all sat in a
a fairly small metal box with an
external 12-volt wall type power supply.
It all went together reasonably well.
So, we got some hardware up and running
in quite quick order, and put it in
front of Adrian.
Yeah, that's where it got fun.
So, did all the electronics speak to
each other at that point or
Pretty much. There were some minor
things. There always are some minor
things, but the fundamentals, it worked.
It talked to its controllers. It spoke
Ethernet, which was smiles all around.
Excellent. And what was Adrian's
software remit at that point?
Well, we started Kevin already had a a
very simple task switching sort of
operating system for the Hitachi 8-days.
So, we had to write everything from
scratch, basically. This is the first
time we'd done anything with Ethernet,
and so the software had to handle
Ethernet packets at the lowest level of
bytes that come in.
The hardware didn't even have DMA, so we
had to actually have a loop in the
software to transfer byte by byte from
the Ethernet controller to receive
packets and send packets. So, very, very
simple, very basic stuff.
What's DMA?
Uh sorry, direct memory access. These
days, Ethernet controllers will transfer
the packets directly into memory. They
will handle whole queues of packets
being stored for you, all behind the
scenes in the hardware, and the software
can then go in and look at the header of
a packet and manipulate it without
having to bring anything else in from
memory even. So, very quick. But, back
in in those days, the Ethernet
controller was so simple, we had to
literally read byte at a time off a
packet and put it in memory, and then
write it out a byte at a time to send it
out to the other controller to send it
on its way. So, very low-level. And we
had to write everything from scratch,
building up from there with IP and TCP
and HTTP for web interface and so on.
So, a lot of a lot of work in the
software.
And this was what, 1999?
Yeah, that's when we started. And this
was before modern broadband had even got
off the ground. The very first
Firebricks were coming out in terms of
working hardware as we were installing
the very first broadband lines. So, it
was really early on.
Wow. And what does a Firebrick router
look like now?
Well, it's moved on. Back then, it was a
small metal case, one WAN port, so the
wide area network, the outside, and four
LAN ports as a hub. These days, we have
two main products. The smaller one's
very similar, it's a slightly bigger
metal box. It still has five ports on
it, but they can be configured pretty
much any way you like. And you can even
plug in a fiber on this small box, which
is kind of aimed at the sort of home or
office gateway product with fire
walling.
But, we also have a larger rack-mount
one U high 19-in rack-mount box, which
provides internet grade gigabit routing.
And we're working on the successors to
both of those, where we're looking at 10
gigabit. But, they're all made in the
UK, unlike a lot of routers and
firewalls. So, it's all sort of designed
hardware and software and actually
manufactured in the UK.
Thanks, Adrian. What I think we'll focus
on for the rest of the show is the kit
that you can get now. It's a good
journey, and I'll make sure we put some
links in for those that want to look at
the original chip sets. So, I'm going to
move us on, Adrian and Kevin, and we'll
talk about, let's say the a version
that's available this year or the past
couple of years, and we're going to talk
about the various decisions you had to
make or selecting the components to
build the router I think would be a good
place to start.
It's probably worth thinking a little
bit about what we're selecting right now
in terms of the hardware for the the
next generation as well as part of this
I suspect.
Yeah, if that fits better, let's let's
go for that cuz obviously you you've got
new decisions to make and supply chain
changes with what's going on in the
world.
That is the biggest issue at the moment.
Yeah, so version is there a version
train for these things? What you calling
the next gen one that you're working on?
Well, the current product for the small
devices is the FB 2900 and the current
data center product, which is very old
now, is the FB 6000.
So, is that the one you're looking to
redo?
That is in the process. There is very
nearly a product called an FB 9000.
We have prototypes.
We have prototypes. They work. The it
isn't finished, but it's very good work
in progress. The biggest limitation to
when it'll be something people can buy
won't actually be development for a
change. It will be component
availability. As you touched on just
now, supply chain issues.
They affect us just like they're
affecting pretty much the entire world.
There are components which are
completely ordinary components from a an
engineer's point of view, but if you try
to buy, they'll tell you you might be
able to get them in 52 weeks, but we
can't even promise that. It's
unprecedented. We've never seen anything
quite like it. So, we do have a very
good manufacturing company who assembles
the PCBs for us and does the buying, and
they're doing the best job they can of
finding things. We just have to hope
that that comes up trumps soon enough.
So, let's take a step back from supply
and if either yourself, Kevin, or Adrian
wants to take us through the design
process of this is what we'd like to put
in it. This is how we think it's going
to work. We can write some software with
it, but until we actually get our hands
on it, we're not going to know if it all
works because
That is very much the challenge here
that looking just at the data sheets,
you have a very good idea that it will
do what you want, but exactly the
details
we're building the FB 9000 with 10
gigabit ports for example. But it's
likely to be maximum of 10 gigabit
throughput through those even though
there's two ports because of the way the
hardware works. And we didn't really
appreciate exactly how that's going to
play together until we have the boards
built and the software working and we
run performance tests and work out
that's the best it's going to do on
those ports, which is fine for the
product we want to build here. It's a 10
gigabit ISP grade router mainly as a an
LNS, which is what handles things like
broadband connections. So it's really
good for that. And the two ports provide
redundancy, but learning that lesson is
complicated process that you you can't
just glean from a data sheet sadly.
Yeah, you also have to match customer
expectations for the fact they've got
two ports.
Oh, very much so. And and now we
understand exactly how this works.
That's going to be very clear in the
documentation that the two ports are
primarily for redundancy, which is a
very important factor in the data
center. You typically connect them to
different switches in the cluster so
that if you have to
reboot a switch for any reason or it
fails, everything carries on seamlessly,
which is essential when you're running
ISP grade type stuff.
So if you were to take the case off of
the FireBrick 9000, what would you see
before you component-wise?
Oh, they look lovely.
What you'd see, you'd initially see a
heat sink covering the main event, the
the CPU underneath it. If you took the
lid off that, you'd see a CPU which
looks superficially like the CPU in a in
a PC or something. It isn't. It's not an
X86 base system. It's an arm base
system. In this particular case, it's
one from TI and it's got four cores
running at about 1 and 1/2 GHz, I think.
Again, by modern PC standards, that
doesn't actually sound a huge amount,
but the way it works with our systems,
which Adrian will explain later,
actually gives incredibly good
performance with that hardware. Around
that, you'd see a very large PCB with a
couple of fans on it. The whole
philosophy of Fibre bricks for data
centers has been to engineer them to
last. So, there's two fans. It's
actually marginal whether a fan is
needed at all because another nice thing
about arms is they're very low power,
but it's going to carry on working even
if one fan fails. The whole thing is
done like that. The power supplies,
which form a fair bit of the design, are
very overrated. The end result of this
is it's very efficient. It runs very
cool and it's
Pretty green as well in that respect,
low power.
it is indeed very green because the CPU
uses a very low amount of power for the
job it's doing. Along the front of the
the case, you'll see a row of 10 SFPs.
We've decided for the data center units
to stick with SFPs rather than have any
copper ports at all.
And what does that stand for for the
non-networking listeners?
What is it?
SFP.
One of those acronyms we use all the
time and and you don't necessarily know
what it exactly stands for. Yes.
Pass on that.
Apologies. They
it's just an industry bit of jargon, I
guess.
But it's a shell with a connector that
lets you plug in your choice of network
connection. It could be a single fiber,
dual fiber, which is more common
transmit and receive, or even a copper
port like an ordinary ethernet
connection. And you can choose what to
plug in. That's that's the key thing
there.
Yeah, it's a a little rectangle square
that you slot them in. I think it's
small form pluggable or something like
that.
That could well be the case, yeah.
sounds like it. Yeah,
I'll I'll put some links in.
So, then at the side sides of this unit,
carry on with the description, there are
two power supply boards. We're using a
bought-in modular power supply, which
takes incoming mains and turns it to 12
volts.
We have two of them for resilience as
well, of course, two completely separate
mains feeds. They're combined on the
main board. And all right, pretty
flashing lights at the front above the
ports, pretty much describes the whole
thing.
One of the the clever things there that
Kev hasn't mentioned is that in a data
center, where you want to plug the power
at the front or the back, is always a
controversial issue. Some some kit has
it at the back, some at the front, and
sometimes you want the network
connections at the back or the front,
and it it's a pain in the neck. And what
we've chosen to do is make these power
supplies reversible. You can have them
both at the back, both at the front, one
of each if you really wanted, which
would be a little bit bizarre, but they
unplug and swap round.
Yeah, so that's the the standard sort of
cupboard size rack that you'd slide a
bit of equipment to for the listeners
that aren't familiar with rackable
equipment. You see it on nice marketing
pictures.
Yes.
So, one of the main business use cases
for the whole thing was that there was
nothing like this that you wanted out
there.
And it's extremely power efficient.
Yes, these days, of course, there's lots
of different routers, especially for an
internet service provider, but when we
started, having a firewall itself wasn't
even something that you necessarily had.
When broadband first launched, one of
the clever things the very early models
did is they they could sit in your
network and firewall, and they had to do
this because the routers you could get
from BT at the time would have a single
subnet on them. You'd have a sort of
joining subnet to connect between your
router and your firewall, and then
another one on your firewall these days.
But, you couldn't do that with the BT
router. It had a single subnet and
didn't have any firewall. So, what you'd
get as a broadband service didn't have
firewalls. People weren't attacking your
network. It was rare. When we first
started, you'd look at the logs and say,
"Oh, someone's attacking me. This is
exciting." It's not like that these
days. It's a steady stream of all sorts
of attacks. So, there really wasn't
anything back then and there wasn't
anything we could just buy in and use.
There weren't Raspberry Pis, for
example, which you might just entirely
write your own software on.
So, we had to start from scratch. And
we've taken that philosophy forward. And
the current fabric, we revamped it
completely when we moved to an arm
platform. So, we started from scratch.
Completely new ethernet controller and
drivers and network stack. And we we
built in IPV6 from scratch at that point
as well. So, the current version of
internet protocol, IP version 6, is is
built in from the ground up in the
software now.
Thank you. And Kevin, you touched on the
CPU as an arm 64-bit. Is that correct?
This one's actually an arm 32-bit.
Okay. Is that what we've got in our
mobile phones or
No, you've probably got something more
advanced in your mobile phones these
days.
The things that we tend to use in
industrial control are usually a few
years behind the cutting edge that
appear in phones. Because one of the
things, supply chain issues aside, is we
want continuity of supply. And
industrial parts tend to be things that
you can design now and you can still buy
them for manufacture in a decade's time
if you need to.
But, as a result of that, they did they
tend to be a little behind the the front
edge. But, they're perfectly adequate
for switching 10 gigabits of ethernet,
which is what we need them to do for
this product. So,
And is there a concept of RAM on or
memory in this?
Very good point. There is. There's a
single SODIMM socket, which I think we
have 8 gigabytes of SDRAM, which doesn't
sound again a huge amount by modern PC
standards, but actually for a router,
it's plenty.
Oh, it's luxury.
I can't remember what we started with.
It was tiny.
The very first brick had a megabyte.
That's it. Yes.
So, 8 gig is quite a luxury.
Thank you. That's a a good summary of
what we've got today, I think, either
for the latest model or, you know, up
until that point. You can argue forever
on this one, I think, but which is the
hardest part, the software or the
hardware?
Actually, I would concede on this one,
the amount of work that goes into the
software exceeds that in the hardware.
So, it's also never-ending. The hardware
is a discrete thing. Once you built it
and it's in manufacture, you don't need
to do a great deal apart from component
sourcing.
Oh, I remember the days when software
was like that and you could make
software and it was put in a mask ROM
and it was done. But, now it is
never-ending now.
So, are you constantly waiting for
Adrian, Kevin?
It's not quite like that. I I tend to be
moving on to the next product in the
line by the time Adrian's in in full
flow on the current product. It's just
that there's a a phase shift. The
hardware has to exist before the
software can be done, but once it
exists, there's often some more hardware
needs to be done. So,
To be fair, you do make it sound a
little bit like it's just me and Kev. We
do now have a bit of a team working on
all of this and thankfully, I'm not
having to spend all of my time working
on the software at the moment and the
same with the hardware. There's people
doing PCB layout and things like this as
well. So, it isn't just the two of us,
thankfully.
Thank you. And if you feel confident
enough, could you give me one disaster
that you overcame? An example of
Oh, easily. Software or hardware?
I'll give you a minute on each. You go
first, Kev.
Okay.
Well, we've not had any huge disasters.
In the current FB9000, which it it's
most topical. We've had a few
challenges, in particular to do with
clock chips. That's probably something
that that as a radio guy
is is going to be quite obvious to you,
but things like 100 MHz oscillators are
not trivial things to make good. We're
using bought-in ones. Well, it turns out
there's actually a huge difference
between different oscillators from very
good manufacturers in practice, in
particular with jitter.
And we did have one particularly thorny
problem, which took a while to diagnose,
which turned out to be one brand of
oscillator jittered in a way which
prevented 10 gigabits from working well,
which is obviously a fairly fundamental
thing for a 10-gigabit router.
That gives you your timing, does it?
Yes, the basic timing for the processor
and the Ethernet subsystems. It was
difficult because you had to be looking
at it in the right way to actually find
it electrically. If you looked at it
with the normal tools, oscilloscopes,
frequency counters, it was bang on.
But the jitter showed up best as a
spectrum analyzer plot, where you could
see, as well as the peak at 100 MHz in
this case, there were sidebands of noise
far higher than they should have been.
And once we got rid of those, suddenly
the 10-gig was working rock solid.
trick was just use a different
manufacturer.
In this case, and we'd had some that
worked, so we knew the 10-gig worked.
It's just it didn't when we some of the
prototypes, so
But that comes down to,
you know, almost 30 years experience how
to troubleshoot things and
Yeah, very much so. Yeah.
And the time delay with getting a new
component as well to test.
As well. So, that's probably the closest
we've had to a disaster on the the 9000
in terms of design.
I think we had something with the 6000
where the the first ARM processor we
were using turned out to be a horrible
bulge of different components at
different speeds and behaved very
strangely, and we essentially moved on
to a completely different chip
afterwards, didn't we?
That's a good point. The first one was a
very early Intel XScale, which is
another ARM architecture, and it was a
it was a three-chip chipset,
and they didn't integrate very well.
Fortunately, we never ended up having to
use that in production because Intel
came up with a one-chip solution, which
worked far better.
And that's when we started the software
from scratch to to do the ARM software,
and thankfully that was the same
software on that other chipset
essentially very minor changes, so we
could move forward.
In terms of the software, I'm not sure
disasters necessarily, unless you count
OSPF, but
we can mention that later, but we have
had some challenges.
That's a routing protocol, guys, for
anyone that's listening. Routing
protocol.
It's it's a horrible routing protocol,
but that's just my opinion. We did have
some interesting challenges when we
started all this and we had these the
smaller FireBrick because
we were only selling very slow broadband
lines, like 500K, we only had a 2
megabit link into BT in our offices in
Reading, and that grew surprisingly
quickly. Broadband was a thing we were
just trying out as will this take off,
and we we had no idea.
And so we stopped selling new lines
quite quickly because people would have
slow service, but we ended up having to
build into the FireBrick traffic shaping
to manage the speeds of business and and
residential customers at different times
of day, and and time profiles to
understand what time of day it was. And
we built those features in very quickly
into the software to handle the demand
for customers on a small link while we
waited for BT to spend months installing
a bigger link for us in a data center.
So, we had to work fairly quickly to
overcome a requirements change that we
weren't expecting in the early
FireBricks, and they're still in there
now, those features.
That gives you some reassurance or quite
a lot of reassurance that your software
development practice is in good shape
because you can move quite quickly and
get those things in place with
confidence.
Oh, definitely. And we we've had to do
some Well, you're going to ask about
features later, which I'll explain some
of the things that we've done during the
pandemic, for example, where we've had
to react quickly to changes in
requirements.
Excellent. I think that's a good place
to move us on to Adrian's remit now and
his team, the operating system. Thanks,
Kevin, for that last bit. So, you've
designed the hardware and you've got to
have some type of operating system to
speak to it. Can you take me through
process management network stack?
Yeah, the key thing here is the
operating system isn't like the
operating system you may be familiar
with in a PC or a Linux box or something
like that. There you have an operating
system as a sort of baseline, you can
then install your own programs. And the
operating system has to protect the
users from themselves very much because
it could be any program. With an
embedded system like this, the operating
system does play an important role. It
does manage the different processes and
memory management and semaphores and
signals and so on, but it's not having
to quite play the same role where it's
unexpected end user software being
thrown at it. The whole system is
tightly controlled. It only runs our
software. So, there isn't quite the same
dividing line between the operating
system and the application that you
would see normally. In some ways, that
makes life a lot easier, but in other
ways, it means the whole lot's one big
product we have to manage and test all
together rather than separate things
necessarily. The original simple process
switching stuff that we had in the very
first OS was redone as part of moving
towards an ARM processor.
And it has to allow lots of different
processes to run. Although, they're
generally not starting and stopping
dynamically. They can do, but mostly
they're all fixed processes that do a
particular job as part of the overall
function and have to work together with
each other and and messages between
them.
So, that's the sort of process
management, if that makes sense.
So, that would be a Is it a process or a
demon or a server that would take in
network packets and then do something
with them?
Yeah, there's actually a a surprisingly
large number of processes. You can go
into the web interface and get a list of
them. So, there are things to handle
packets. That's mostly done on
interrupts well than a separate process.
We try and shift packets in and out as
quickly as possible. But there are there
are processes to handle each protocol.
So, things like BGP, VRRP, and so on.
DHCP, they all have processes that run
and there are queues of packets that go
into those processes that they then
handle and and send out packets. The the
whole job is packets in, packets out one
way or another.
And so, if we had a packet come in
through the Ethernet interface as it
were, could you take us through a flow
of that?
Yeah, sure. There's fortunately we do
have this DMA, direct memory access. So,
we get an interrupt to say there's one
more packets waiting. And there's two
key sort of paths to those packets. If
we're passing the packet through, we're
acting as a router or as a firewall or
doing network address translation,
whatever. The packet comes in, we work
out where it's going, and we may have to
make changes to the header uh if
the simplest just being the Ethernet
address it's going to to send it on to
the next gateway. But we may have to
make changes in the IP layer for things
like network address translation and
even add or remove headers for tunneling
protocols. But we make those changes and
we send the packet on its way. And
that's all handled in the interrupt move
that packet in and out as quickly as
possible. However, there's a lot of
functionality where the fabric is the
the end point of the communications. So,
any of the protocols accessing its web
interface, talking BGP, DHCP, etc.
involve the packet coming in and being
put in a queue. That queue then causes a
process that's waiting for packets on
that queue to run, pull in that packet,
do its job, and send it on its way. And
that's handled more as a sort of main
task that's task switched between the
different processes. Um the queues have
semaphores, so it wakes up the right
process.
And that's separate from the shift
packets in and out as quickly as
possible for booting.
You mentioned the word semaphore there.
Could you just explain to the listeners
what that is and how you use it in the
router?
Yeah, it's a flag or a counter sort of
thing. It's used for things like knowing
whether there's a message in a in a
queue or if you need to to lock out two
things trying to do something at the
same time. And it's important that it's
part of the operating system because you
can have a a process waiting on a
semaphore. It's waiting until a packet's
ready or something. And so the operating
system knows not to even try running
that process cuz it's waiting. And as
soon as the semaphore is is set to the
right state, it can then add one or more
processes that's waiting onto the queue
of processes to run and make sure they
all run when they're meant to.
Is that similar to a mutex or is that
something completely different?
Well, it's all part of the same
mechanism in in the operating system.
It's used for a mutex where it's a
semaphore that's just one or naught. But
it can also be used as a counter.
And does this go back to what you said,
Kevin, about the oscillator being the
key thing to make sure that all moves
along at the right speed predictably?
The oscillator is the fundamental system
clock which all computers have. In a
way, yes, it's a bit like a metronome,
but rather higher speed telling the
insides do something, do something, do
something. The whole architecture of
modern electronics works around that,
like it's heartbeat.
Yeah, so the software does have a sort
of like a heartbeat. It has timers, it
has functions that run periodically. But
a lot of what we're doing is is based on
queues of packets. So the interrupt
controller says it's got a packet, puts
it on a queue for a particular process,
and then the operating system has to
decide which process to run next
depending on which processes are more
important or which have been waiting too
long, which have things waiting in their
queue, and it makes that decision and
runs the relevant process to handle that
that next job.
So, what looks after if one of these
processes has an issue, or is slow, or
disappears?
Ah, well,
it's an embedded system. So, as I said,
it's a little bit different to your
average user programs running on a PC,
where yes, they can hang up or go wrong.
Basically, they don't, or rather, they
shouldn't. So, no, a process can't
really lock up like that. It has to get
on and do its job. There are built-in
software and hardware watchdogs, just in
case something unexpected does happen,
and that actually causes the whole
system to reset and generate a report
that's emailed to us to tell us that
something is stupid has happened, and
those are relatively rare.
It's not like a PC, where you might stop
that task and restart it. It shouldn't
stop. That's the whole point.
Okay, thank you. And you spoke about the
packet coming in, depending on what it
looks like, it can might go straight out
to its next hop or end point,
or the router itself might have some
type of services on it that it will use
that packet for, and make replies and
things. So, obviously, that has loads of
different protocols involved in there.
You had to write them all, I take it?
Absolutely. And when a packet comes in,
it's just a sequence of bytes, and you
have to break it down, and it starts
with with MAC addresses, and then it has
IP Internet Protocol IP headers, and
then it might have UDP or TCP or IPsec
or something else, and then there's
payloads in that, and even when you get
up to TCP, you've then got protocols on
top of that, like HTTP for the web
pages, and BGP, for which is a routing
protocol, to manage routes between
routers. So, all of these layers have
their own protocols, and we've had to
write everything from scratch to do all
of that, largely because of where we
started from. There weren't readily
available embedded system IP stacks you
could use. So, we had to write them, and
these days, it's it's more policy. We've
had to write them, we build on them, and
we do write all of them in protocols.
And what was your language of choice for
all of this?
Ah, yes.
One of your trick questions here. It's
all done in C. There's a little bit of
assembler, there has to be in any
low-level operating system, but we use
C. None of us are really keen on C++.
So, it's all in C, and we're very
experienced C coders. But, the other
thing you you did ask before we started
here is what would we use if we would
start again. And we've discussed this a
bit, and we've actually considered the
possibility of even using Ada because of
the very strong typing and controls it
gives.
Even C programmers though with lots of
experience do sometimes need these extra
controls to make sure things don't
break.
Yeah, we did a show on that, and I'll
put in the link notes.
Show notes rather about Ada. I did a bit
of research on that after. It's quite an
interesting language, too.
It is interesting, but I think because
it got mandated for military projects,
everyone shied away from it, which is a
shame because it's quite a good
language.
And it's not something that a lot of
people say, "Oh, you should use Rust for
everything." But, that's not something
that would work in this type of
environment.
but C's what we use because that's the
experience we had when we started.
That's where we're coming from in terms
of what we've used most in the past.
Okay, thank you. I'm going to move us on
to how you test all of this next cuz
lots of different moving parts. So,
obviously you're selling these things,
so there's certain legal and government
type certifications you need to put on
things.
So, that will probably help with what
you need to get tested and certified.
Can you just take us through what a
modern router in 2022 needs to have for
it to be able to be plugged into a data
center?
A lot of it is very similar legislation
to any electronic product. I must say
electronic testing standards have
improved immensely in the years I've
been in in business.
Back in the day, equipment often didn't
work with each other, failed in
silly, bizarre ways
because there was no testing. There is
now. Effectively, we have two types of
standards we have to comply with. First
is electromagnetic compatibility, both
for emissions and immunity, and secondly
is for safety. Obviously, both are
rather important things. EMC makes sure
that you can have one piece of equipment
sat next to another piece of equipment
and they don't interfere with each
other.
In a data center rack full of equipment,
that's absolutely fundamental to the
whole thing working. Secondly, safety
testing, you can't be too safe.
And there were devices in the past which
literally burnt buildings down because
they weren't thoroughly thought through.
Not our devices. I I second we we always
follow the safety standards and often
exceed them, whatever they are.
But, in order to sell a product, you
need to put a CE mark or now a UKCA
mark, which is pretty much the same
thing, on it. And in order to do that,
you need to make sure that it does meet
the standards. And in practice, the only
way to do that is to employ a test
house, certainly for the EMC. In
practice, what that means is you send
your product or go along with your
product to a test house and they work on
it for typically about three or four
days, running all sorts of tests,
pointing aerials at it and bombarding it
with quite high energy RF, having very
sensitive receive aerials listening to
see what's coming out of it, sending
nasty spikes and surges up the mains
inputs and any other connections that it
has. And if it survives all this and is
still working at the end and hasn't
radiated anything that it shouldn't do,
then it gets a pass.
And how much of that do you have control
over? I mean, sorry, from the point of
view of you've potentially put some of
your own electronics in to make
components speak together. Obviously,
the components are manufactured by the
manufacturers, so they'll have some type
of certifications they've got. So, do
you have to tweak your power supplies
that you've built or the
Very much so. It It's more a case of
just good engineering practice. Very
often, a lot of problems for complex
systems are in power supplies or poor
grounding is a is a good one.
If the grounding isn't right, you'll get
currents flowing in paths that you
shouldn't do. And even down to cabling,
the layout of cables within boxes can
pick up bits of mush from one component
and carry it straight out the front
panel. So, it's down to experience
again. Once you've been through a few
EMC tests, you you learn pretty quickly
the kind of things that affect it, and
you make sure your next design is as
good as possible before you go and test
it.
And all things being well, it'll be
okay. We've got a good track record in
that now, but the very first things,
like anybody,
you learn as you go.
Thinking back to my uni days and RF
stuff, it's all a bit of an art, isn't
it? RF engineering, radio frequency
engineering.
Very much so. And it does help to have
some people, which we do know, who are
very much into RF to advise certain
things. A lot of it, like so many things
in life, turns out to be common sense
once you think it through, but it's not
necessarily easy stuff to think through
if you haven't grown up in the field.
Thank you. And so far, from the network
side of point of view,
Ah. Well,
in some ways, life's a lot easier
because there isn't formal testing you
have to do before you can sell a network
product. And that might sound like it's
easy, you don't have to do all this
certification and sending off to test
houses, but on the other hand, you
haven't got someone you can send it off
just as easily and say, "Does it all
meet these specs?" So, you have to do a
lot of in-house testing and a lot of
testing of does it work with other
products?
The specifications are in most cases in
in RFCs, the network standards that
exist.
Writing the protocols to follow this OSC
strictly is great, but you don't always
find everything else quite follows them
perfectly. So, sometimes you have to
find a lowest common denominator in
terms of how the protocols work to to
work with the most other equipment. And
we've had to do testing things like we
have a complete voice over IP telephone
system in the Far
providers and check how they all work
together and identify when they don't
and work out the best way of making them
work even when we're doing it right and
someone else is doing it wrong, we still
try and make it work if we can.
So, would this be a case of you've
looked at the request for comments the
RFC standards that everyone works on to
agree a a common way to do something.
You've taken that protocol, you've gone
through the the must it must do this and
it may do that.
Yeah, must, may, should and all this.
Yeah, and you found that the musts are
not all there or
Well, the one of the problems is that
not all these protocols are necessarily
operating completely in isolation. So,
you you may have firewalling getting in
the way of allowing a protocol to work
the way it was designed. Particularly
voice over IP phones, they they can work
with a subset of the RFC. Um, we've gone
through many iterations of of making a
voice service for Andrews & Arnold and
we now use Fibrix as our core voice over
IP service. But the early iterations, we
expected to be able to do in a certain
way to have lots of different sort of
call routing back ends. And then we
found loads of phones can't cope if
they're told to do a call set up to one
IP address, but the actual audio goes to
another one, for example. They just
won't do it even though the RFC says
they should. So, we've had to design the
system to to be, as I say, lowest common
denominator. We only use one codec,
which is a codec everybody uses as a
common one, rather than doing any
conversion. So, we have to make these
decisions in terms of designing the
protocol. And sometimes we design
protocols with extra features, as well.
Our Voice over IP deliberately has
situations where it won't respond to
requests, even to say no, you're wrong,
because that then tells someone
attacking your network that you've got a
Voice over IP server sat there, and
they're going to go ahead and keep
attacking till they get in. So, we have
settings where if you're trying to talk
to a Voice over IP server from outside,
even though that's allowed cuz you've
got some phones that people working from
home or something, it won't respond
unless you've got all the credentials
right. Whereas from the inside, it'll
respond and say no, you've got the
password wrong, try again, sort of
thing. So, which means technically we're
not following the spec. We're meant to
respond, but we have an option to say
don't do that on the outside. So,
sometimes we extend protocols.
Sorry, that fits nicely with our OWASP
show that was just came out for our
security vulnerabilities, cuz that would
be just like a
website's login page where it says that
user doesn't exist or that user exists,
your password's incorrect. So, it's that
type of hiding.
Exactly. And in this case, we're we're
actually not responding at all. You
know, we're not a VoIP server.
We're not answering, because that's the
the best way to to not then get hammered
with lots of different password
requests.
And these types of tests, do you do any
sort of unit tests or integration tests
on the software side before you actually
test the protocols live? Do you have to
create your own protocol simulators or
are there test tools for that?
In some cases, we have to simulate the
protocol. In a lot of cases, we can set
up other equipment that already talks
the protocol to test it. So, during
development we we will sometimes be
setting up several different, you know,
like a Linux box or a PC or as I said,
several VoIP phones to test. On occasion
we've had to create something
specifically to simulate the protocol,
but you always run into the problem
there that if you create your simulator
to how you've read the RFC and you
create your code to how you've read the
RFC, especially if how you've read the
RFC isn't quite correct, it'll work
perfectly because they're talking to the
to the same understanding. So,
simulators that you've made aren't
always the best answer. We do have a
test setup that is used for performance
testing and regression testing before
software builds come out. This is sort
of several different versions of
Firebrick and various other equipment
that communicates with it to do various
tests.
Yeah, we've done quite a few shows on
software engineering and testing where
that exact point you've raised, where
the test is only as good as the person
that's written the test and if they've
written the code, the test is generally
going to pass, so
it's best to have those slightly
separate.
if you've got a team where it's
different people that do different
things, but even then there's no
substitute for some real world testing
as well with other equipment and other
manufacturers just to make sure
you're not getting the wrong end of the
stick somewhere with how it should work.
I'm going to have to move us along a bit
to try and get as much covered as I can,
but can we just finish up this section
on testing with how you bring in
security testing for these and one
example of something that you found that
you you had to fix?
I'm not sure I can think of I mean,
security is one of those things you
always have to be working on and always
improving.
We've improved things like how we do
password hashing, that sort of thing
just as as later standards come along,
but as I said, we don't have to do any
formal testing before you sell a product
like this, but we do have a lot of our
customers that been involved in formal
penetration testing of their networks
protected by Firebricks. So, we know in
that environment we pass those tests
with no problems. Mostly, it's our own
testing to try and work out at Cambium
Actifibre rather than separate test
houses for that.
Okay, and and is there anything that you
can recall in the specs that you or the
feature set of a protocol that you
thought you'd done and was picked up?
Can I just add something here? We have
implicitly had testing done in customers
premises. Lots of our customers use
Fibrox to protect their networks and
they have had those pen tested by
professional pen testing companies. So,
we know that there have never been any
problems with any of those sorts of pen
tests. I know it's it's not a sort of
scientific way of doing it, but uh real
world we've been implicitly tested more
than once.
I'm going to move us on to you've built
the software, you've tested it, you're
happy with it, but that's not the end of
it. So, you've got to keep constantly
fixing any issues that come up or
handling feature requests. This is
commonly called the release cycles of
software train as it were.
So, can you tell us a little bit how you
deal with release cycles or if you get a
feature request?
The releases are are fairly
straightforward in that we have
obviously we can build the software
ourselves with changes as we're working
on them to to do testing.
We will then make an alpha release and
this is something that's on the Fibrox
website and you can download an alpha
release. Normally, customer Fibrox won't
run one of these alpha releases. The
customer needs to speak with us first
and say that they want to try out an
early release of software and will
enable it on their Fibrox. And this
helps avoid just people being gung-ho
and saying I want the latest software
and and then getting code that doesn't
necessarily work 100%. So, we do have
some customers that do load these alpha
releases and it's usually when we're
working with someone on a on a feature
change or or request that they've got,
we will do ongoing alpha releases
regularly, sometimes several a day,
sometimes you know, could be a week
apart,
but we'll release these so that people
who are testing them can try them out
and give us feedback. When we're happy
with a a milestone that we've got, new
features, or or we want to make a
release, then we make a beta release,
and this is available to everybody.
Anybody can load one of these, but
Fabric doesn't automatically loading a
beta release. You have to tell your
Fabric you want to be a bit more leading
edge and try the beta release. And if
there's any problems, we'll withdraw
that. And that's happened a couple of
times where we've done all our testing,
we've had customers doing various
testing on alphas, we've done a beta,
and someone's found something
significantly wrong with it that we need
to withdraw it, fix it, make another
beta release. Happens occasionally, but
not very often.
What sort of thing would that be?
Uh yeah, I knew you were going to ask
that. I'm trying to think, but it it
it's quite a while since we did that
last time, so I'm not sure I can
actually think of a specific example for
that, to be honest. It's usually the
sort of thing where there's a customer
with something very obscure in their
setup that isn't part of our normal
testing, cuz there's so many different
ways people can use a Fabric that we
can't test every possible way. We have
to test each each subsystem as much as
we can, but some of the combinations of
working We have had occasions where
that's happened, but I can't think of a
specific example.
So, presumably you then incorporate that
test for the next time.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, once a beta has
been released, usually for a few weeks,
and we we test it on our core network as
well to make sure, especially for for
ISP infrastructure, we want to make sure
there aren't any issues with that. And
then we promote that to a full release.
At that point, most Fabrics will
automatically upgrade that over the next
24 hours at some point. And most people
don't even notice their Fabric upgraded.
It downloads the new software
automatically, it re-flashes it, it
reboots, and the reboot is well under a
second. So, most people don't even
realize their Fabric upgraded. The core
network ones in data centers are not set
to do that. Mostly, the IT people
involved in those want to carefully
manage when they do an upgrade, and so
so they'll look at a release note from
us and decide when to do it. But, the
smaller Fireboxes automatically upgrade.
But, we give customers a lot of choice
about how much risk they want to take.
Customers can be loading alpha releases
if they want. They can load betas, they
can load releases. They can even set the
system to say, "I don't want to release
until it's been out for 2 weeks, just in
case something happens." And they can
tell their Firebox, "Don't load it
straight away when it's available. Leave
it some time."
They can tell it to only do it in the
middle of the night if they want. So,
they've got a lot of control. Or they
can tell their Firebox not to upgrade.
We obviously don't recommend that,
especially as it's a a security product
with firewalls and things. If we are
improving features or security, it's
best if everyone gets an upgrade. But,
you can do that, even.
And are you able to share, happy if you
say no,
uh how you get a user to opt in to run
an alpha? You know, what are you
changing there? Is that a software
toggle or a hardware toggle or
Uh yeah, we have settings in a in a in a
database in terms of
what a Firebox's capabilities are. And
we can change those and provide a a new
signed configuration for the Firebox so
that it then knows it's allowed to load
an alpha release or not. Both the code
and the configurations are all digitally
signed. Well, it's called capabilities
in our setup rather than configuration.
Configuration's what the customer does
to set their Firebox up. The Firebox's
underlying capabilities are a digitally
signed bit of XML data that can be sent
to the Firebox so it knows it's come
from us.
And do they have to ask you to resign a
bit of something? Yeah. Okay, that makes
sense. So, they can't just go and
download it because they're
No. It's to protect customers from
themselves, really. We we know there are
plenty of people who say, "Oh, I want
the latest alpha software." And we don't
make any guarantee that the alpha
software actually works. It's mainly for
the people who are looking at the
features we're we're working on now to
try out, rather than just for everybody.
And is that how you validate everything?
Is PGP signatures or some private key or
There's different security for different
things. So, there are the code as I say
is signed and so is this capability.
But, things like IPsec tunnels and HTTPS
certificates and so on are all managed
in different ways. So, things like HTTPS
certificates are managed typically using
Let's Encrypt and that's also what a lot
of people use for IPsec where they
validate the domain name at the end
using a Let's Encrypt certificate. So,
there's there's different levels of
Yeah, I meant the software and the
firmware, sorry.
The firmware is digitally signed and and
it's it's a different signature level
for alphas and releases. So, even though
there's a team of software engineers,
only
specific people can can sign a release,
for example.
I'm going to move us on to the last
section of the show. It's gone really
quick.
So, just to summarize again, so got the
lessons where we are. There was nothing
like this out there, efficient or low
power at the at the time and you've
evolved with that. You're a C engineer,
so that was the right choice at the
right time and still is today. Extremely
feature rich and low energy use
equipment. You can upgrade them on the
fly, but they need to be told how to do
that. And you use all the standard
protocols.
default, a customer fabric will just
upgrade itself with new releases
automatically. You don't have to do
anything special with that at all. It's
only the alpha releases that we treat
specially like that.
So, we've got the ongoing life cycle of
the product and it's all certified and
and tested. But, now as a a user of that
system and product, I want to make a
change. And that's a whole different
thing, isn't it? It's managing
configuration,
validating that, checking the user's not
messing their own thing up.
Yes, but
change it remotely. You can support a
product.
It's very easy for people to think, "Oh,
yeah, I'll just create a network
operating from scratch with the
hardware."
But, until it gets out there in the real
world, you there's so much more that
you're missing. So, could could you take
us through the ongoing configuration and
upgrades that you have to think about?
Well, customers configure their own
fabrics. As an ISP, when we sell
fabrics, we do offer a service to help
someone configure their FireBrick if
they want for a small fee. And we also
provide sample configurations for their
broadband lines. So, if you if you buy a
broadband line from us on a FireBrick,
we can say, "Well, here's the starting
point for your config. It understands
your logins and everything for your
broadband to work and and firewall
settings to to protect your LAN and
here's something to get started."
That's a good point. I haven't actually
said that this router isn't just to work
with your own ISP. It can work with
anything.
Uh yes, it's it's an Ethernet level
router. So, it works with Ethernet, but
it it works with PPP protocol as well.
So, if you've got a a broadband modem,
it will work with that. I've got one on
a Starlink satellite here acting as a
gateway to work as a backup, for
example. So, that there's lots of ways
you can use this. In terms of the
configuration, we made a decision very
early on to make a single definition of
the configuration. And this this is XSD
based. It's an XML protocol to define
XML, which is just all a bit incestuous.
But, it defines all of the settings and
fields in the configuration. And that
single master file is what generates all
of the the headers and definitions in
the C code. So, the actual code using
the config,
it also generates a published XSD so
people can actually use it with tools to
validate the XML config if they want
themselves, and people do that. It
generates the manuals for the config
fields. It generates the JavaScript
based web config editor. So, on the
config web page, you go in and it's got
icons and labels and fields you fill in
and help text. All that's generated from
this single master definition.
Obviously, that's what gets updated when
we add new things to the config, but it
means that they're all consistent. And
we've seen so many routers where the
command line has some config settings
that don't exist in the web interface or
or the saved file or whatever. With the
FireBrick, they're always consistent
because they're made from a single file,
which I think is an important feature.
Yeah, I I one of the things that a user
engineer that you experience over your
lifetime
is evaluating products and you know, the
life cycle of upgrades. You've got to
constantly check the change logs. You
know, is this deprecated? Is this still
there? If you do it on the XML side of
things, you can instantly do that, can't
you?
Well, one of the reasons XML was chosen
as the underlying config format is that
it's it's extensible. The clue's in the
X.
So, when we add new features, we
generally try to make sure that you
don't have to mess about with the config
when you do an upgrade. It's partly why
the upgrades are automatic. You don't
have to think about the config chance on
working. The new features are extra
fields or or settings which, if
necessary, have defaults so that they
just become available as new features.
And we we don't very often deprecate
something. So, XML's worked really well
as the config, but you can edit it in
XML even to the web interface. But, a
lot of people use this web-based sort of
graphical interface to edit it where you
can go through different icons and
listed sections and open them up and
fill in the fields. So, we have this
relatively easy to edit web-based
config. But, one of the things you were
saying that, you know, there's nothing
like trying this out in the in the field
with real customers. One of the
important things with a a router and a
firewall is customers can dig themselves
in a hole.
You can very easily configure the
firewall to shut you out. And that's not
too bad if it's sat in front of you.
There's a factory reset process.
But, if it's 100 mi away in a data
center, that's a pain. And one of the
features we put in, I mean, it wasn't
there in the beginning, it was a few
years ago, is a test config. And you
press test and it applies the config and
if you don't do anything for 5 minutes,
it puts it back. So, when you lock
yourself out, you just have to wait 5
minutes and then it starts working again
and you can work out what you did wrong.
Of course, if it does work, you can then
say now make the config permanent. So,
that was an invaluable feature we put in
to help users protect them from
themselves and make it so you can test a
config. And we certainly recommend it.
You can even make it so that a certain
user on the fire brick can only test the
config first. If they make a change and
they you define which users are allowed
to make changes and which aren't, you
can say, "Yes, you're allowed to make a
change, but you have to press the test
button. Only when you've done that can
you then commit it."
And is this a benefit of using XML for
that type of thing or just a a design
pattern?
That could have been done with whatever
type of config we used. It's not really
an XML specific thing, but we chose XML
because it's extensible. That's what's
stored in memory. It's also something
people can work with remotely. It's very
easy to to to use external tools to
manage XML and we know lots of customers
who generate configs on the fly using
other systems in XML because it's such a
standard. And actually we do that on our
core routers. We take the XML from the
router and we set certain things and
send it back to the router. or the fire
brick. So, it's very easy to write tools
to manage XML and that's another reason
we're using it and it works really well.
And was it always like that with the XML
configuration or was it something
I can't remember the very first fire
bricks. I I think XML came in with the
rewrite for arm, I think.
It was web-based only the very first
fire brick.
it. Yes. Yes. And when we moved to arm,
we decided on this single config
definition and all XML based.
And I know a lot of our listeners will
be thinking about the time that they've
used XML and SOAP APIs and
they'll be thinking why not JSON or
something like that.
Well, I I don't
spoke to Kevin about this earlier. I was
saying if we did it now, it might well
be JSON. Uh it's XML and it may as well
stay like that. Mostly people aren't
editing the XML. Mostly they are working
with the the web interface, the
graphical interface. But XML works for
this purpose. It's fine and to be fair,
when we started the XML
that was the thing everyone was doing.
Um JSON really didn't get a look in back
then.
These days, perhaps it it be a different
decision.
And you've got a that does it, it's
tested, it's you know, it's mature, it's
been out in the field. It would need to
be a major decision really to justify.
Well, we'd almost certainly engineer it
so that you could do XML or JSON and
there'd be a compatible translation
between the two. But yes, it would be
yeah.
That that would be something to think
about depending on you know, if enough
customers come to us saying that we
really want to work in JSON not XML,
then then we might consider it.
Thank you. That takes us up nicely to
we're starting to wrap up the show.
Could have done a show on each of those
subtopics. It's really difficult
to give an overview and get enough
technical details. So thank you for for
that. I think we've done a great job of
covering what goes into not only
specking up a router, you know, the
history of it, the components, the
testing of the hardware,
the software, and building everything
from scratch. And but if there's one
thing you'd want, I don't know, a senior
software engineer to take away from our
show, what would you want it to be? You
know, what what's the the thing that
you'd like to instill?
We did think about this and to some
extent
it's really that reinventing the wheel
is not always a bad thing. The history
of the fabric means we weren't just
reinventing the wheel. We were coming up
with new things from scratch because a
lot of what we wanted to do wasn't
there. But reinventing the wheel is is
what we get accused of a lot because
particularly these days where you know,
putting voice over IP on there, we could
have taken a standard off-the-shelf open
source voice over IP platform and
tweaked it to work on the fabric. And to
be honest, I think if we'd done that, it
wouldn't be anywhere near as good. I
think we've done a much better job
because we we did it from scratch. So I
think the message there is don't be
afraid to reinvent the wheel sometimes.
You know, I mean, not always, but it's
definitely worth considering.
We hear that a lot actually and you see
it on some of the articles online and
some of the sort of thought leaders in
the software engineering space where
sometimes, you know, a less feature-rich
specific version of something is better.
Absolutely. I I've seen I mean,
obviously as part of doing this we've
considered other libraries, and I do
lots of other software. And I'll look at
a library to do something, and sometimes
you'll find a library is so bloated and
so much, and what you actually want is a
tiny subset. And so, sometimes it's
actually a lot easier to just write that
specific bit that you need. Other times,
you'll see a library where it doesn't
work very well. Or, particularly with
the FireBrick, the way we we handle
packets efficiently and and try to do
something at a very low level as fast as
we can and reliably means you have to
write it in a different way to a
conventional operating system or for an
embedded system. So, sometimes the
libraries out there just don't fit, but
sometimes they're too big and you want a
small bit. So, it's it's always worth
considering.
And Kevin, would your message be always
make sure you've got a good earth?
That's a good one. That sums it up
nicely. I like that.
You've got to be well grounded to be a
hardware engineer.
Yes.
Was there anything we missed that you'd
like to mention?
The only other thing I
you asked about features, and we didn't
really cover it. We We do take feature
requests from customers. We try to do
things if we think lots of customers
will want them, or sometimes if we think
it's a really nice feature. And in the
pandemic, we did have to react quite
quickly to requests from several people
who wanted a high availability internet.
They wanted to be able to use multiple
internet connections at once, and if one
of them broke, not drop a packet because
they're doing things like this podcast
recording here is all done over the
internet. And if your internet drops
out, even if it's quick and fall back
and only takes a minute, it breaks
things. And we had people like judges
doing video conferencing from home and
things like this, and they wanted a way
to do high availability when a link
breaks, cuz it will, they don't lose
anything. And we created a custom
package based on L2TP and multiple links
and tunnels to do this, and it's worked
very well for them, but it was it was a
case of us having to react to changing
circumstances that that one could
predict, and implement a feature
fairly quickly for some customers who
were in a fix. And that's the sort of
thing we still do. We still try and
react and meet our customer
requirements.
So, when a feature request comes through
like that, do you have to bypass your
release cycle and alpha beta?
No, no, we still do that. That's where
the alpha releases really come into
their own. So, a feature like that might
be
especially where it's a completely new
feature. We can include it in the
fabric, label it experimental. We can
include it in this particular version of
the build of the fabric that's only
available to some people. And and we can
include it in alpha releases so that
people who want to try it can without
upsetting our normal releases. But
ultimately, it does then end up in a
normal beta release and then a release.
I think I've got time quickly for one
last question.
When you look back at the whole thing,
yourself and Kevin and your team, and
you have your list of protocols or
hardware, is there one thing there you
that you go, "Wow, we did that." Or is
it just the whole project as a whole?
What makes you, you know, gives you that
smile when you go to bed at night, when
you've had a rough day, you think, "Ah,
it doesn't matter. I did that."
I would say just the fact that we have
products that we're essentially running
our businesses on.
Yes. Yes, that's that's a good point.
They sit there working 24 hours a day
and do a good job.
Yeah. One of the features we put in was
constant quality monitoring, monitoring
every single line every second on our
broadband network, and that has allowed
us to pull apart major problems in
people like BT's network because we've
had this monitoring and they don't. And
so, we're this tiny player as an ISP,
and we went in and told BT they have
core network problems and proved it. And
the monitoring graphs ended up on
reports to BT directors and things like
that. And I thought, you know, that's
amazing that we're a small manufacturer
and a small ISP, and we're talking to
the to the big guy like this and saying,
"No, fix your network."
And that's because you know inside out
and can prove every bit of your own
stock and hardware that is definitely
not you. And Excellent. So, where can
people find out more? They can follow
you on Twitter or
Well, Farbic website farbic.co.uk.
There's I suppose there's not a lot on
there apart from the release notes. We
we do obviously when we come out with
new products we put a lot on there. And
there is a Twitter account doesn't post
very often if at all. So, yeah, what do
you think Kev in terms of the best way
Best way to get in touch with us after
looking at the website is either pick up
the phone or give us an email. We're
very approachable and if it's something
appropriate you can talk directly to the
people actually designing things.
Sometimes that's what someone wants.
And you've both got your own Twitter
account don't you? And Adrian you've got
a blog right here.
Yeah. The blog probably when I'm doing
something new on the Farbic or coming up
with a new idea that's often on my blog.
So, that's well worth looking at. You
can get us on an IRC channel as well
believe it or not.
Perfect. Adrian, Kevin thank you for
coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. This is Gavin Henry for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5.
Thanks for listening.